[Music]
foreign
walks into the ER with intractable
hiccups one of the questions the
emergency room physician should ask is
you've been eating star fruit
am I video cautioning about oxalate rich
foods I talked about star fruit
nephrotoxic kidney toxicity excessive
consumption of star fruit has been
associated with the development of
oxalate kidney damage less than a cup of
star fruit juice or three whole fruits
they're not that big can result in acute
star fruit
nephrotoxicity ingestion of even modest
quantities the star fruits can produce
kidney problems
so it's essential to educate the public
to avoid consuming star fruit especially
on an empty stomach or in a dehydrated
state to prevent starfruit
nephrotoxicity but what about the
neurotoxicity we've known for more than
a quarter Century now about the
neurotoxic effects but few seem to be
familiar with the syndrome it starts
most commonly with hiccups but then can
rapidly worsen especially in those with
compromised kidney function to start out
with and why because the fruit contains
a powerful neurotoxin that can
accumulate in the blood cross the
blood-brain barrier and eventually cause
irreversible brain damage the toxin
itself named cram box and is uh normally
excreted by the kidneys and so it's
especially toxic to those with renal
insufficiency compromised kidney
function so much so that for those with
severe chronic kidney disease a single
star fruit can put someone in seizures
within three hours a coma and then death
within three days
in a series of about 100 cases of
toxicity consumption range between just
a half a star fruit up to 50 with an
average of about four but most of those
had some sort of pre-existing kidney
disease the average number of star
fruits eaten by the normal kidney
function group before they're toxic dose
is more like 15. so people with normal
kidney function may be more likely to
suffer from kidney damage than brain
damage which starts it down around about
four star fruit the bottom line is that
those with chronic kidney disease should
avoid star fruit to avoid severe
intoxication in Brazil where the fruit
is popular they're actually laws to
alert people about the risks
because of the neurotoxin star fruit
should be prohibited for patients with
chronic kidney disease and even those
with normal kidney function may want to
avoid the fruit
just something to think about before you
reach for the stars
[Music]